A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of the Vice President, Office Files of David Bell FA624
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office of the Vice President, Office Files of David Bell
1966 - 1981
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA624
16.28 Cubic Feet
The papers of David Bell, Vice President of the Ford Foundation's International Division from 1966 to 1981, document his activities at the Ford Foundation and those of the International Division during this period. They were sent to the Foundation's Archives in July 1981 by Alice Maloney, who served as Secretary and Executive Assistant to Mr. Bell for the duration of his tenure. The papers consist primarily of correspondence, memoranda, and Bell's rough notes summarizing meetings and conferences attended. They are divided into six series. The series' order is based on substance and size. Arrangement of files within a series corresponds closely to the original order established by Ms. Maloney. The papers are particularly rich in the following areas: • the activities of the International Division: the Office of the Vice President and the overseas field offices (Series I) • the annual meetings of the Board of Trustees and its subcommittees (Series II) • the activities of the international agricultural center system, including the Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research (Series IV) • the Foundation's Population Program (Series V)
Biographical / Historical
David E. Bell, Executive Vice President of the Ford Foundation's International Division, was a member of the Foundation staff from June 1966 until his retirement in August 1981. During this period, he held the following positions:
• March 1969, Executive Vice President, International Division • June 1966, Vice President, International Division
David Bell was born on January 20, 1919. He received his B.A. degree with highest honors from Pomona College of Claremont, California, in 1939, and was elected Phi Beta Kappa. In 1941, he earned an M.A. in Economics from Harvard University.
Prior to Bell's career with the Ford Foundation, he held the following positions:
• 1942, Budget Examiner, U.S. Bureau of the Budget • 1945-51, Assistant to the Chief, Fiscal Division, The White House • 1951-53, Administrative Assistant to the President, The White House • 1954-57, Field Supervi sor, Pakistan Planning Board Project, IIE - Harvard University, Pakistan • 1957-60, Lecturer, Economics; Secretary, Graduate School of Public Administration, Harvard University • 1961-62, Director, U.S. Bureau of the Budget • 1962-66, Administrator, Agency for International Development
After his retirement from the Foundation, Mr. Bell joined the Faculty of the Harvard University School of Public Health.
Mr. Bell's personal papers have been donated to the John F. Kennedy Presidential Library. Other papers are at the Harry Truman Presidential Library.
Scope and Contents
David Bell's papers document his Foundation activities from 1966 to 1981, particularly in the following areas:
• the International Division: the Office of the Vice President and the overseas field offices; • the Board of Trustees and its subcommittees; • the International Agricultural Center system, including the Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research and the International Food Policy Research Institute; • the Foundation's Population Program.
They reflect Bell's involvement with policy development and implementation, program and budget planning and administration, administrative procedures, and meetings and conferences for the following programs in the International Division: Office of the Vice President (OVP), Asia and the Pacific (A&P), Europe and International Affairs (EIA), Latin America and the Caribbean (LAC), and Middle East and Africa (MEA).
The papers contain materials on a review (the Overseas Development Self-Study, or "0peration Janus", initiated by F. Champion Ward) and reorganization of the Foundation's international activities into programs based upon geographical areas. There is also material on the planning and implementation of the 1979-1980 Program Reviews in preparation for the second Foundation-wide program reorganization.
For Ford Foundation International Division meetings and conferences from 1966 to 1979, the papers contain lists of participants, agenda, notes for discussion, and notes or memoranda summarizing the proceedings. There is also material on the planning and administration of special programs such as the International Division Programs for Women for the years 1975 to 1980. Other topics of special interest include Bell's meetings with the Chinese delegation of December 1980 and the Ford Foundation Pakistan Reviews of 1969 and 1979.
Bell maintained a flow of correspondence with Foundation colleagues and Trustees, Heads of State, ex-USAID colleagues, and grantee and other philanthropic organizations. Of special interest is the correspondence between Bell and such individuals as McGeorge Bundy, Henry Ford II, Alexander Heard, Soedjatmoko, and Patricia Ward, and such organizations as the Council on Foreign Relations, the Overseas Development Council, and several agencies of the United Nations.
For the meetings of the Ford Foundation Board of Trustees and its International, Executive, Finance, and Communications Committees for the years 1966 to 1980, the papers contain lists of participants, agenda, notes for discussion, and notes and/or memoranda summarizing the discussions. Of particular interest: the Special Board Review Meetings of 1976, and the Board of Trustees Meeting in India (1978).
During Bell's tenure, the Foundation was instrumental in the development of eight international centers for agricultural research. The papers are rich in material on five of the eight centers: the International Rice Research Institute (IRRI), the International Institute of Tropical Agriculture (IITA), the Centro Internacional de Agricultura Tropical (CIAT), the International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center (CIMMYT), and the International Crops Research Institute for the Semi-Arid Tropics (ICRISAT). The papers document the centers' growth, their program planning and administration, and meetings and conferences from 1966 to 1981. There are lists of participants, agenda, notes for discussion, and Bell's notes summarizing the proceedings.
Most of the agricultural center material is related to: the activities of the Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) and its Task Force on International Assistance for National Agricultural Research (ISNAR) for the years 1971 to 1976; the annual meetings of the International Centers Week for the years 1970 to 1979; the Ford and Rockefeller (Bellagio) Meetings on Agriculture and Development (1969-1970, 1975); and the activities of the International Food Policy Research Institute (IFPRI) for the years 1974 to 1979, as it sought and gained entry into the CGIAR system. Other topics of interest include the respective roles of CGIAR and the United Nations and Agricultural Organization (FAO) in agricultural development (1978), and the review of donor support to CGIAR and the centers (1979-1980).
The Population Program expanded considerably during Bell's tenure. The papers contain material on program planning, administration, and evaluation for this period. For the Ford and Rockefeller (Bellagio) Conferences on Population and Development from 1968 to 1979, the papers contain lists of participants, agenda, notes for discussion, and notes summarizing the proceedings. There is also material on the collaborative discussions with the Rockefeller Foundation on Roy O. Greep and Marjorie Koblinsky's "Reproduction and Human Welfare: A Challenge to Research" (1976); the subsequent meetings with Joseph Califano to discuss alternatives to abortion (1977); and a review of Ford Foundation field staff comment on Sol Chafkin's Health/Nutrition/Population (H/N/P) proposal to the Foundati on (1978-1981).
Finally, Bell retained material on selected Foundation procedures, divisions and offices of the Foundation other than the OVP/ID, selected subject areas in which grants were made, and selected surveys and studies. Of particular interest is the material on the Tax Reform Act of 1969 and the ID follow-up; and the Task Forces on Finance, Procedures, and FAPs (Foundation-Administered Projects).
Arrangement
The papers of David Bell are divided into six series:
I. International Division Files
II. General Correspondence Files
III. Trustee Meeting Files
IV. Agriculture Files
V. Population Files
VI. Subject Files
Separated Materials
Some groups of papers have been removed and placed with the appropriate record groups in the Ford Foundation Archives:
• Files of F. F. Hill/F. Champion Ward/W. P. Gormbley • International Division Budget Papers • International Division Program Review Papers • Ford Foundation Conference Papers • Minutes and Dockets of Trustee Meetings • Staff and consultant reports and publications.
Their locations have been noted on cross-reference sheets. A list of titles of reports removed from the papers is appended to this register. Papers not related to Ford Foundation activities have been pulled and discarded.
Conditions Governing Access
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Ford Foundation
- International Division Files, 1966 - 1981; I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, International Division Files (1966-1981), is the most extensive. It contains material on the activities of the Office of the Vice President (OVP), International Division; its re-organization in 1966, and its administrative policies. There is extensive material on the program planning and administration of the Division's overseas field offices in the four program areas in effect at that time: A&P, EIA, LAC, and MEA (Asia & Pacific, Europe and International Affairs, Latin America and the Caribbean, and Middle East and Africa). The substantial Budget sub-series includes material on the Program and Budget Reviews of 1979 and 1980. There are also files on the annual meetings and conferences of the International Division, and on the Overseas Development Self-Study of 1966-1967 ("0peration Janus").
  Arrangement
  This series is divided into the following five sub-series:
  A. Office of the Vice President Files (1 box)
  B. Field Office Files (4 boxes)
  C. International Division Meetings and Conference Files (2 boxes)
  D. International Division Budget Files (4 boxes)
  E. Overseas Division Self-Study Files (0.5 boxes)
  - Office of the Vice President Files, 1966 - 1980; A
    This sub-series is further divided into two sections. The first section consists of general material on the organization of the International Division. It is arranged chronologically. Within each folder, the correspondence is arranged in reverse chronological order.
    The second section consists of files on International Division administration and special programs. It is arranged alphabetically by folder title. Within each folder, the correspondence is arranged in reverse chronological order.
    - International Division - Organization, 1966 - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ford Foundation Reorganization, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - ID Organization - Europe and Far East, 1967 - 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - ID Organization (Zeidenstein/Nelson), 1968 - 1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Office of the Vice President/Int'l Division (General), 1966 - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - ID Committee on Women, 1975 - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - ID Control Unit - (ID Grant-Making), 1966 - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - ID Control Reports, 1974 - 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - ID - Delegation of Authority, 1966 - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - ID - Discretionary Awards, Travel and Study, 1967 - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - ID/OVP - Education, 1969 - 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - ID/FF Programs for Women, 1975 - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - ID - Rosters, 1967 - 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Field Office Files, 1966 - 1981; B
    This sub-series is further divided into four sections: the Asia & Pacific (A&P), Europe and International Affairs (EIA), Latin America and the Caribbean (LAC), and Middle East and Africa (MEA) programs of the International Division. Within each section, the folders are arranged alphabetically, and within each folder, the material is arranged in reverse chronological order.
    - International Division - Asia and Pacific (ID/A&P), 1967 - 1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - International Division - Asia and Pacific (ID/A&P), 1971 - 1979 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - ID/A&P - Afghanistan, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - ID/A&P - Bangladesh, 1971 - 1974 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - ID/A&P - Burma, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - ID/A&P - China, 1978 - 1979 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - ID/A&P - China, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - ID/A&P - China China Conference, CSCPRC - 9/8/80, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - ID/A&P - India, 1967 - 1974 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - ID/A&P - India, 1975 - 1980 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - ID/A&P - Indonesia, 1966 - 1979 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - ID/A&P - Japan (and other East Asia), 1967 - 1971 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - ID/A&P - Japan (and other East Asia), 1972 - 1975 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - ID/A&P - Malaysia, 1974 - 1975 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - ID/A&P - Malaysia Review, April 15, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - ID/A&P - Pakistan, 1967 - 1978 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - ID/A&P - Pakistan, Pakistan Review, Sept. 1969, 1969 - 1970 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - ID/A&P - Pakistan, Pakistan Review, Dec. 1979, 1979 - 1980 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - ID/A&P - Philippines, 1966 - 1981 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - ID/A&P - Sri Lanka, 1966 - 1974 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - ID/A&P - Thailand, 1967 - 1975 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - ID/A&P - Vietnam, 1972 - 1975 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - International Division - Europe and International Affairs (ID/EIA), 1966 - 1979 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - ID/EIA - Arms Control Meeting, Jan. 1979, 1978 - 1979 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - ID/EIA - Canada, 1967 - 1979 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - ID/EIA - Ford Foundation Strategy Towards Europe, 1972 - 1973 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - ID/EIA - Greece, 1968 - 1971 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - ID/EIA - Information and Discussion Papers, 1966 - 1968 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - ID/EIA - Paris Office, 1969 - 1975 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - ID/EIA - Southern Europe, 1968 - 1975 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - ID/EIA - USSR and Eastern Europe, 1967 - 1975 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - International Division - Latin America and the Caribbean (ID/LAC), 1966 - 1980 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - ID/LAC - Other Latin America, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - ID/LAC - Argentina, 1971 - 1976 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - ID/LAC - Brazil, 1970 - 1974 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - ID/LAC - Caribbean, 1966 - 1980 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - ID/LAC - Central America, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - ID/LAC - Chile, 1972 - 1979 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - ID/LAC - Colombia, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - ID/LAC - Mexico, 1974 - 1978 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - ID/LAC - Peru, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - ID/LAC - Venezuela, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - International Division - Middle East and Africa (ID/MEA), 1966 - 1978 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - ID/MEA - Africa General, 1969 - 1980 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - ID/MEA - Congo and other West Africa, 1967 - 1971 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - ID/MEA - East and Central Africa, 1976 - 1979 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - ID/MEA - Ghana, 1966 - 1967 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - ID/MEA - Nigeria, 1967 - 1977 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - ID/MEA - North Africa (Former Tunis Office), 1968 - 1971 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - ID/MEA - South Africa, 1969 - 1980 (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - ID/MEA - Middle East (General), 1966 - 1977 (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - ID/MEA - Middle East Review, June, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - ID/MEA - Lebanon and Beirut Office - Regional, 1966 - 1976 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - ID/MEA - Iran (Former Office), 1967 - 1979 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - ID/MEA - Iraq, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - ID/MEA - Jordan, 1962 - 1966 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - ID/MEA - Turkey, 1967 - 1979 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - ID/MEA - UAR, 1967 - 1979 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - International Division Meetings and Conference Files, 1968 - 1979; C
    This sub-series is further divided into two sections: International Division divisional meetings and conferences, and International Division meetings and conferences on selected subjects. Within each section, the folders are arranged chronologically, and within each folder, the correspondence is arranged in reverse chronological order.
    - ID Conference - Nairobi, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 72)
    - ID Conference - Nairobi, June 1968 - Summary Notes (Box 5, Folder 73)
    - ID Conference - Mexico City, Dec. 1969, 1969 - 1970 (Box 5, Folder 74)
    - ID Conference - New Delhi, Oct. 1971 - General, 1966 - 1971 (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - ID Conference - New Delhi, Oct. 1971 - Discussion Paper - FF Staff Comments (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - ID Conference - New Delhi, Oct. 1971 - Discussion Paper - Outsiders' Comments, 1971 - 1972 (Box 5, Folder 77)
    - ID Conference - New Delhi, Oct. 1971 - Summary Notes, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - ID Conference - New York, Sept. 1973 - General (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - ID Conference - New York, Sept. 1973 - Agenda and Summary, 1973 - 1974 (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - ID Conference - New York, Sept. 1975 - General (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - ID Conference - New York, Sept. 1975 Agenda and Rapporteurs' Reports (Box 5, Folder 82)
    - ID Conference - New York, Mar. 1979 - General, 1978 - 1979 (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - ID Conference - New York, Mar. 1979 - Agenda, Summary Papers, 1978 - 1979 (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - ID Conference - New York, Mar. 1979 - Principal Agenda Papers (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - ID Conference - New York, Mar. 1979 - Follow-on (Box 6, Folder 86)
    - ID/A&P: Asia Meeting on Education Singapore - Oct. 1970 (Box 6, Folder 87)
    - ID/MEA: Africa Program Review, New York - Nov. 1970 (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - Nigeria Board Meeting (postponed) June 1974, 1973 - 1974 (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - ID Education Conference Oct., 1979 (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - International Division Budget Files, 1967 - 1981; D
    This sub-series is further divided into the following sections: general files on the ID Budget, ID Budget Program Review files, and Bell's notes on selected subjects re: ID Budget/Program Reviews. Within each section, the folders are arranged chronologically. Within each folder, the correspondence is arranged in reverse chronological order.
    - Resource Base Allocations - FY 1968, 1967 - 1969 (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1969, 1968 - 1969 (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1970, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1970, 1969 January - April (Box 6, Folder 94)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1970, 1969 June - October (Box 6, Folder 95)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1970 (Box 7, Folder 96)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1971, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 97)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1971, 1971 - 1972 (Box 7, Folder 98)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1972, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 99)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1972, 1972 - 1973 (Box 7, Folder 100)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1973, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 101)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1973 (Box 7, Folder 102)
    - International Division Budget - Planning and Evaluation Agenda - General, 1971 - 1973 (Box 7, Folder 103)
    - International Division Budget - Planning and Evaluation Agenda - ID Responses, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 104)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1974, 1972 - 1973 (Box 8, Folder 105)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1974, 1974 January - March (Box 8, Folder 106)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1974, 1974 April - October (Box 8, Folder 107)
    - International Division Budget - "Papers on 1980 Budget", 1974 (Box 8, Folder 108)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1975, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 109)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1975 (Box 8, Folder 110)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1976, 1976 - 1977 (Box 8, Folder 111)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1977, 1977 January - March (Box 8, Folder 112)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1977, 1977 April - December (Box 9, Folder 113)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1978, 1977 - 1979 (Box 9, Folder 114)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1979, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 115)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1979, 1979 January - April (Box 9, Folder 116)
    - International Division Budget - FY 1979, 1979 March - November (Box 9, Folder 117)
    - International Division Budget FY 1980, 1980 January - April (Box 9, Folder 118)
    - International Division Budget FY 1980, 1980 May - August (Box 9, Folder 119)
    - International Division Budget FY 1980, 1980 September - December (Box 9, Folder 120)
    - International Division Budget Balance of Payments, 1967 - 1971 (Box 9, Folder 121)
    - International Division Budget Dependent Organizations, 1968 - 1970 (Box 9, Folder 122)
    - International Division Budget Dependent Organizations, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 123)
    - International Division Budget Endowment Grants, 1967 - 1977 (Box 10, Folder 124)
    - International Division Budget Foundation Size, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 125)
    - International Division Budget Grant Status Reports - Backlog, 1975 - 1980 (Box 10, Folder 126)
    - International Division Budget Overhead Charges, 1970 - 1971 (Box 10, Folder 127)
    - International Division Program Reviews - Commitment Status, Year-End Balance of Appropriations, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 128)
    - International Division Program Reviews - General, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 129)
    - International Division Program Reviews - A&P, 1979 - 1980 (Box 10, Folder 130)
    - International Division Program Reviews - EIA, 1979 - 1980 (Box 10, Folder 131)
    - International Division Program Reviews - LAC, 1979 - 1980 (Box 10, Folder 132)
    - International Division Program Reviews - MEA, 1979 - 1980 (Box 10, Folder 133)
    - International Division Program Reviews - OVP, 1979 - 1980 (Box 10, Folder 134)
    - International Division Program Reviews - POP, 1979 - 1980 (Box 10, Folder 135)
    - Division Reserve - Current, 1977 - 1981 (Box 10, Folder 136)
    - FY 1981 Budget, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 137)
    - O&M Issues - Oct./Nov. Meeting, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 138)
    - OVP Meeting - 9/30/80, 1979 - 1980 (Box 10, Folder 139)
    - Thomas' Oct. Meetings With Representatives, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 140)
    - Thomas' Program Review Meetings July 1979 (Box 10, Folder 141)
    - Thomas' Program Review Meetings Oct. /Nov. 1980 (Box 10, Folder 142)
  - Overseas Division Self-Study Files, E
    Th is sub-series is arranged according to the order in which it was originally received and consists of material on the OD Self-Study - "0peration Janus". Within each folder, the correspondence is arranged in reverse chronological order.